<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the English army now in Scotland, touching the justness &amp; necessity of their present proceedings in that nation. Imprimatur Joh: Rushworth.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D666</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E609_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205957</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865172</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865172</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117409</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82143)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117409)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 93:E609[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the English army now in Scotland, touching the justness &amp; necessity of their present proceedings in that nation. Imprimatur Joh: Rushworth.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Husband and John Field, printers to the Parliament of England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>August 12. 1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117409:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE Engliſh Army NOW IN <hi>SCOTLAND,</hi> Touching the Juſtneſs &amp; Neceſsity Of their preſent PROCEEDINGS in that NATION.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Joh: Ruſhworth.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward Huſband</hi> and <hi>John Field,</hi> Printers to the Parliament of <hi>England. Auguſt</hi> 12. 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117409:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117409:2"/>
            <head>For the Under-Officers and Soldiers of the Engliſh Army: From the People of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T concerns you, as you deſire not to imbrue your hands in the blood of the Lords people without a cauſe, and to be anſwerable to the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge of the World in the day of your Accompts, to conſider whether the Invading of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> wherein we, and all our Intereſts are included, be not a thing moſt ſinful and unlawful, which will bring wrath and indignation from the Lord upon all thoſe who are engaged therein, or acceſſory thereto. And becauſe we know that things are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented to you, and you are made to believe, That your Undertaking is Juſt and Neceſſary; We ſhall therefore, for your Information, ſhortly ſhew you how unwarrantable the gounds are, upon which your ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Parliament have concluded and commanded to Invade this Land; that, if it be poſſible, your ſin and our affliction may be avoided.</p>
            <p>The firſt Ground which is hinted at in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ſo called Parliament, is, the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Scotland</hi> their Uſurping upon Acts of Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117409:3"/>Power, and their frequent pretenſions to, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations about a joynt Intereſt in ſome Acts of it, whileſt they were reſident in <hi>England,</hi> and whileſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Friendſhip and Unanimity in the ſame Cauſe was pretended: But it is moſt certain, That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> did never claim, nor aſſume to themſelves any power concerning the making or giving of Laws in <hi>England:</hi> The moſt that they did, was, 1. The Committee of both Kingdoms being appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the joynt Reſolutions of the Parliament of both Kingdoms, they acted therein in a co-ordinate way in things of common Intereſt. 2. They did often, by Letters and otherwiſe, repreſent to the two Houſes of Parliament their deſires, and give them Warning when they were either negligent in, or averſe from their duty in the work of Uniformity. 3. They pleaded for a joynt Intereſt in the Kings Perſon, he being King of <hi>Scotland</hi> as well as of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond, and a main Ground of Invaſion, which is much inſiſted upon, is, The late unlawful Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt ENGLAND in the year 1648. But how Unjuſtly and Unchriſtianly this is charged upon this Kingdom, will appear to you in theſe particulars: 1. That Engagement was proteſted againſt in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by a conſiderable part of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament it ſelf, even thoſe who at firſt entred into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with <hi>England,</hi> and ſent an Army for their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and are now in place and power in <hi>Scotland.</hi> 2. Not onely did the Body of the Miniſtery of the Land preach and pray againſt it, but all the Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Kirk did ſupplicate the Parliament againſt it, and the General Aſſembly did in the very time of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117409:3"/>the going forth of the Army, publiſh a large Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt it. 3. As many Committees of War in Shires did petition the Parliament againſt it; ſo were the Body of the people of the Land, eſpecially the godly, ſo unſatisfied with it, that as they did cry to God againſt it, ſo did they refuſe to contribute there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and concur therein; and becauſe of this, ſuffered great affliction and oppreſſion from a prevailing party of Malignants who carried it on. 4. Thoſe who had proteſted againſt it in Parliament, and the generality of the well-affected in the Land, did before the defeat at Preſton, begin to ſtir in Arms againſt it, and did not lay them down, until they had got all power out of the hands of that party that carried it on. 5. The Houſe of Commons and Lieut: General <hi>Cromwel</hi> by their Letters, the one to the General Aſſembly, the other to the Committee of Eſtates, do in a large way bear Teſtimony to the Innocency of the honeſt party in <hi>Scotland</hi> in that particular, and did alſo give them Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt thoſe who carried on that Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>The third Ground is, The proteſtation given in by the Commiſſioners of this Kingdom at Weſtminſter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the taking away of the Kings, and changing of the Government; but this, as it was an innocent and harmleſs, ſo it was it a neceſſary Duty, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Irregularity and Inſolency of proceeding in theſe things by Men wanting Authority, and the joynt Intereſt of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the Kings Perſon; but alſo becauſe they could not but foreſee the great Scandal, and many ſad conſequences that would follow thereupon to both Kingdoms.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117409:4"/>
            <p>The fourth Ground, is this Kingdoms refuſing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the Damages that <hi>England</hi> ſuſtained in the unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Engagement in the year 1648. But to ſay nothing that it was Injuſtice to demand Reparation of thoſe Damages from thoſe who were Sufferers themſelves: Reparation was not refuſed; but as the Committee of Eſtates gave aſſurance to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> That none who had been active in, or conſenting to the ſaid Engagement, ſhould be imployed in any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique place or truſt whatſoever, without the advice and conſent of the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> ſo did they not refuſe all fair amicable ways of Reparation, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know the particular Wrongs and Damages, and upon knowledge thereof, offered to give juſt Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>The fifth Ground is, A Reſolution of thoſe in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> again to Invade <hi>England,</hi> which is fancied upon very unwarrantable Grounds; as, the refuſing of a Treaty, the Proclaiming of <hi>Charts Stuart</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> and promiſing him Aſſiſtance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>England,</hi> and declaring againſt the party that now prevails in <hi>England,</hi> as Sectaries, &amp;c. To all which we ſay, That this Kingdom did refuſe to treat with your Parliament, not becauſe they had a purpoſe to Invade the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> but becauſe a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing party have taken away the Houſe of Lords, and alſo driven away and impriſoned many Members of the Houſe of Commons, and changed the Government, they could not acknowledge the Remnant for the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority of <hi>England.</hi> And for the King, they did no otherwiſe proclaim him King, then in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way, that hath been followed by both Kingdoms,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117409:4"/>ſince they were both united under one King; and they have given him no promiſe but this, That they will by all lawful Means within their power and calling, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Covenant, contribute their Endeavors for his peaceable Reſtitution to the Government of his other Dominions. And as to the declaring againſt them as Sectaries, it is far from a concluſion of making War againſt them; we can and ought to mourn and pray, and bear Teſtimony againſt then Errors, and yet be far from thoughts of Invading of them: We will aſſure you, That as thoſe Grounds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Declaration of your ſo called Parliament, do not conclude it; ſo hath there not hitherto been any ſuch Queſtion debated, nor any ſuch Reſolution taken in the publique Councels of this Kingdom, but what hath been done here, hath been meerly in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Defence of the Land, if we ſhould be Invaded from <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore it concerns you in your conſciences, as before the Lord, to weigh well whether God will countenance you in ſuch a thing, and whether it be not a fearful breach of Covenant in you, after <hi>England</hi> hath Sworn before God, and Angels and Men, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Union and Peace between the Kingdoms, to come without cauſe to Invade this Land, and make War upon us, and oppreſs us, and ſhed our Blood; we will aſſure you, That all who know God in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> cry to Heaven againſt ſuch Oppreſſion; and you have cauſe to be afraid, That becauſe of the ſame, God will ariſe to execute Judgement upon it: Your quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel now is not againſt Malignants, but againſt thoſe who in the Integrity of their Spirits have been follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117409:5"/>Jeſus Chriſt and his Cauſe, and ſtudying to walk anſwerable to the Goſpel, and who helped <hi>England</hi> in the day of her diſtreſs, and have ſuffered much on her behalf; chuſing rather to endure all the afflictions that the Malice of Malignants could deviſe, then to break with <hi>England,</hi> or ſet one foot in that Land in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile way. Thoſe among you ſhall be wiſe, who ſhall take Warning to proceed no farther in an evil way, leſt God, who is the Judge of all things, look upon ſuch Injuſtice, and Ingratitude, and Breach of Covenant, and require it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117409:5"/>
            <head>To the People of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (eſpecially thoſe among them, that know and fear the Lord) from whom yeſterday we received a Paper, directed, To the Under-Officers and Soldiers of the Engliſh Army;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>We the Officers and Soldiers of the Engliſh Army do ſend Greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AT the beginning of the great and wonderful workings of God in theſe two Nations of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> We the Under-Officers and Soldiers of the Engliſh Army, now in <hi>Scotland,</hi> were moſt of us, if not all, men of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Callings, and not all intereſted in Matters of Publique and State Affairs; but yet very many of us, in whom the Lord had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to reveal himſelf in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt, were ſenſible of the Antichriſtian Tyranny that was exerciſed by the late King, and His Prelates, over the Conſciences, Bodies, and Eſtates of the True Spiritual Church of Jeſus Chriſt; namely, Thoſe that were born again, and united to him by his Spirit; who were then by that Antichriſtian crew, termed Puritans, Sectaries, Schiſmaticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for not conforming to all the Canons and Ordinances of their National Church, were frequently impriſoned, baniſhed, and otherwiſe grievouſly moleſted at the pleaſure of thoſe that then ruled amongſt us. Under theſe ſad ſufferings of the people of God, our ſouls mourned, and underſtanding by the manifold gracious promiſes in the Word of God, That a time of Deliverance was to be expected to the Church of Chriſt, and deſtruction and ruine to <hi>Babylon;</hi> Our hearts, together with all the truly godly in <hi>England,</hi> were exceedingly ſtirred up to pray to the Lord, even day and night, That he would ariſe to deſtroy Antichriſt, and to ſave his People: Whileſt this Spirit of Prayer was poured forth upon Gods people in <hi>England,</hi> attempts are made upon <hi>Scotland,</hi> to bring them to a conformity in Religious worſhip, by endeavoring to impoſe upon them a Popiſh Service Book, which was through the great goodneſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117409:6"/>of God, by his people in <hi>Scotland,</hi> reſerted; which made the wrath of the late King and His Prelates, wax ſo hot againſt them, ſo as <hi>Scotland</hi> had no other way to preſerve it ſelf, but by coming into <hi>England</hi> with an Army; which the godly in <hi>England</hi> did not then count an Invaſion to deſtroy <hi>England,</hi> no more then they do this our preſent march for the ruine of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but rejoyced to ſee ſome appearing againſt that Antichriſtian power that had perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Saints, and were aſſured, That the Lord was come forth to anſwer the many Prayers and Tears that were then poured and pouring forth for that purpoſe; and therefore ſo far as we have any opportunity farthered the deſigns of that Army, ſome of us hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our lives by ſpreading their Book, intituled, <hi>The</hi> Scots <hi>Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and pleading for the Juſtneſs of their Proceedings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us remember how the Lord was pleaſed graciouſly to anſwer the prayers of his people at that time, in their Deliverance from the Army raiſed by the late King, and his Prelates, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of all the people of God in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, That ſoon after <hi>Scotland</hi> ſits in Peace, enjoying their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Liberties, without being impoſed upon by the Antichriſtian Prelacy in <hi>England;</hi> and <hi>England</hi> obtains a Parliament, to whom they have opportunity to complain of their grievances, and through the great goodneſs of God ſo conſtituted, that grievances are heard, and overtures made to the late King for their redreſs, which was ſo irkſome to His Oppreſſing, Tyrannical, and Bloody ſpirit, that he again betook him ſelf to overthrow the Parliament by force, and to that end entertains the Officers of the Army that had gone forth againſt our Brethren of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and withdrawing himſelf from his Parliament, an appearance of a Civil War begins, which bring made known to us, the Inferior Officers and Soldiers of this Army (then in our Private Callings) we found our hearts extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſtirred up by the Lord, to aſſiſt the Parliament againſt the King; being abundantly ſatisfied in our Judgments and Conſciences, That we were called forth by the Lord, to be Inſtrumental to bring about that, which was our continual prayer to God, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The deſtruction of Antichriſt, and the Deliverance of his Church and people. And upon this ſimple account we engaged, not knowing the deep policies of worldly Stateſmen, and have ever ſince hazarded our lives in the high places of the field, (where we have ſeen the wonders of the Lord) againſt all the oppoſers of this work
<pb facs="tcp:117409:6"/>of Jeſus Chriſt, whom we have all along ſeen going with us, and making our way plain before us. And having theſe things ſingly in our eye, namely, The deſtruction of Antichriſt, the advancement of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, the Deliverance and Reformation of his Church, in the Eſtabliſhment of his Ordinances amongſt them, in purity according to his Word, and the juſt civil Liberties of Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: We did many of us rejoyce at the Covenant, becauſe we found in it a ſtrain towards theſe ends, although ſome being more enlightned, did apprehend it to be ſo mixt with worldly intereſt, That they juſtly feared the intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt would be onely pretended to, and the intereſts of this world, yea, of Antichriſt himſelf carried under a vizard, as we have ſince had abundant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of; which hath made us (we confeſs) not to idolize the Covenant (as we fear too many do) though we truſt it will appear before God, Angels, and Men, That we ſhall ever purſue its true and lawful ends, according to the plain and candid meaning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; though we do not upon every occaſion urge the Covenant, (as we ſee every party, though as far different as light and darkneſs, apt to do,) the Lord having by his Word, and by his Spirit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced us of our duty therein, though there had been no ſuch Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant at all entred into:</p>
            <p>But when we ſaw, That under pretence of the Covenant, a corrupt party in Parliament, by their worldly policy, after the war was end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>England,</hi> and the late Kings party ſubdued with the loſs of Thouſands of the lives of Saints (whoſe death is precious in the ſight of the Lord) did endeavor to ſet up the King upon his own terms, and with him to eſtabliſh a National Church Government, not in all things agreeable to the Word of God, but is deſtructive to the juſt Liberties of the True Spiritual Church of Chriſt, which he hath by his own moſt precious Blood purchaſed for them, and is now come forth to beſtow upon them, which did ſufficiently demonſtrate it ſelf by the dealings of the then Maſter Builders with the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, in, and about <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndon,</hi> that were then threatned to be diſſolved, and Laws made to prevent the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints with one another, except onely in that one Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Form then about to be eſtabliſhed, to the aſtoniſhment of many of us that had lifted up our hands to God, and ſworn to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor a Reformation according to the Word of God; and therefore after much waiting upon God by Prayer, and examining our own hearts, about the ends and ſincerity thereof, we were
<pb facs="tcp:117409:7"/>abundantly ſatisfied, that it was not onely lawful, but our duty to keep our Arms in our hands, till the ends before mentioned ſhould be accompliſhed; and to that purpoſe, the Army whereof we are a part, did refuſe to disband, did march up to <hi>London</hi> to propoſe to the Parliament a way of Eſtabliſhment that might be more for the carrying on of the ends of Religion and Liberty, though therein we were not at that time ſucceſsful, yet moſt wonderfully and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly preſerved by the Lord, and extraordinarily convinced, after much ſeeking the Face of God, that our failing was in endeavoring to ſet up the King upon any terms, he being a man of ſo much Blood, that the Lord would have no peace with him, nor any that ſhould go about to eſtabliſh him: Whereupon after his own hard heart had hindred him from yielding to any overtures that were made to him by the Parliament, through whom all the Armies Propoſals were to be tendred, and a ſecond War more dangerous then the former contrived by him, and his Son now with you, together with thoſe in <hi>Scotland</hi> that hated us of the Army of <hi>England,</hi> under the name of Sectaries, being by the unſpeakable goodneſs and mighty power of God waded through, and a ſecond teſtimony given from Heaven, to juſtifie the proceedings of his poor ſervants againſt that bloody Antichriſtian brood, though with the loſs of many precious Saints; we were then powerfully convinced, that the Lords pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was to deal with the late King as a man of blood: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſwaded in our conſciences, That he and his Monarchy was one of the ten horns of the Beaſt ſpoken of, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.12, 13, 14, 15. And being witneſſes to ſo much of the innocent blood of the Saints that he had ſhed in ſupporting the Beaſt; and conſidering the loud cryes of the ſouls of the Saints under the Altar, we were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily carried forth to deſire Juſtice upon the King, that man of Blood: And to that purpoſe Petitioned our Superior Officers, and the Parliament, to bring him to Juſtice, which accordingly, by an high hand of Providence was brought to paſs; which act we are confident the Lord will own, in preſerving the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> againſt all Kingdoms and Nations, that ſhall adventure to meddle with them upon that account: When God executes his judgments upon malefactors, let none go about to reſiſt: when he brings forth thoſe his enemies that will not ſuffer Jeſus Chriſt to be King in the midſt of his Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts, and breaks them in pieces like a Potters veſſel; let not <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor any other Nation ſay, What doſt thou? We fear they have been too buſie already, the Lord that
<pb facs="tcp:117409:7"/>ſees the ſecrets of all hearts, knows the compliance of <hi>Scotland</hi> with the late Kings iſſue now with you, was in order to diſturb the Peace of <hi>England,</hi> for being Gods executioners upon a bloody Tyrant, and a ſupporter of the Throne of the Beaſt: But bleſſed be the Lord, the crafty are taken in their own ſnare, <hi>England</hi> ſits in peace, whileſt <hi>Scotland</hi> receives into their chief City, their new King, at the very hour wherein an Army that had matched 300 miles, is facing them at the very gates. We wiſh our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> eſpecially thoſe that truly fear the Lord, would conſider theſe things, and not ſlight the providences of God ſo much as they do: When <hi>Scotland</hi> choſe new gods, and would have a King out of a Family that God had rejected, then was war in the Gates: And though we do not think Providences alone, a ſufficient rule for Gods people to walk by, yet we do know that the Lord ſpeaks to his people by his Providence, as well as by his Word; and he is angry with his people that do not take notice thereof, and promiſeth bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to thoſe that do, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. and the latter end.</p>
            <p>And here give us leave (not in a boaſting ſpirit, but in meekneſs and fear) to tell you, That we are perſwaded we are poor unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy inſtruments in Gods hand, to break his enemies, and preſerve his people. You have acknowledged us in your own Papers to be a Rod of Iron to daſh in pieces the Malignants, but withal, ſay: We muſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be broken in pieces, becauſe we now ſet our ſelves againſt the Lot of Gods inheritance. Let us here ſpeak for our ſelves, yea, the Lord ſpeak for us, who knows our hearts, and all our ways; we value the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, who are the lot of Gods inheritance Ten thouſand times above our own lives; yea, we do bleſs the Lord we are not onely a Rod of Iron to daſh the common enemies in pieces, but alſo a hedg (though very unworthy) about Chriſts Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard; and if we know our own hearts, where ever the lot of Gods inheritance ſhall appear to be found in <hi>Scotland,</hi> we ſhall think it our duty, to the utmoſt hazzard of our lives to preſerve the ſame: But if there be any that have taken councel together againſt the Lord, and againſt his anointed, when the Lord hath decreed to ſet upon his holy Hill of <hi>Sion;</hi> we are perſwaded the Lord hath brought us hither as inſtruments, through which, he will ſpeak to them in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure. We deſire it may be known to you our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> That we are not Soldiers of Fortune, we are not meerly the ſervants of men, we have not onely proclaimed Jeſus Chriſt, the King of Saints, to be our King
<pb facs="tcp:117409:8"/>by profeſſion; but deſire to ſubmit to him upon his own terms, and to admit him to the exerciſe of his Royal Authority in our hearts, and to follow him whether ſoever he goeth, he having of his own good will entred into a Covenant of Grace with his poor Saints; and be aſſured, it is he that leadeth us into <hi>Scotland,</hi> he hath done in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> And therefore we do in the ſpirit of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly love, and of the fear of the Lord, beſeech you to look about you, for our Lord Jeſus is coming amongſt you as a refining fire, and as Fullers ſope; and bleſſed are thoſe in whom the leaſt dram of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity ſhall be found. We have a Paper directed to us from the people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> it having been publiquely made known to us at the head of our Regiments, wherein we are firſt deſired to conſider the lawfulneſs of our marching into <hi>Scotland.</hi> We bleſs God we did that before we came, and are abundantly ſatisfied, that we are brought hither by the Lord; nay, many of us lying under tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of fleſh and blood, and going about to frame excuſes to take us from this march, found, that to have ſtaid behinde, had been to have turned our backs upon Jeſus Chriſt, and to have deprived our ſelves of much ſweet communion with God, that now through his goodneſs we do enjoy.</p>
            <p>We have alſo conſidered the Arguments, by which you go about to weaken the grounds of the Parliaments, and our Superior Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, leading us into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and muſt needs give you this re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n, That we are ſtill abundantly eſtabliſhed in this belief, that what the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> hath done in ſending us into <hi>Scotland,</hi> hath been of abſolute neceſſity to preſerve them ſelves from being deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Religion and Liberties, which they have been at ſo much coſt both of blood and treaſure, to purchaſe and preſerve; and therefore by the way, we muſt needs tell you, that we cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to hear them called, <hi>A Pretended Parliament,</hi> which we deſire you to take notice of, That if you write to us again, you would ſpeak more reverendly of the Authority of our Nation, or elſe we ſhall eaſily think you will upon every occaſion, be ready to invade <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that you may ſet up an Authority, which you may call law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>And let us, as in the preſence of the Lord, farther aſſure you, That we have already examined our conſciences, as before the Lord, and have a clear aſſurance in our hearts, That he will countenance us in this Action, and that we do not break any Covenant which we have Sworn before God, Angels and Men, but could be contented,
<pb facs="tcp:117409:8"/>ſhould we not thereby Idolize the <hi>Covenant,</hi> to march to any En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with you, if called thereunto by the Lord, with the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> on the Tops of our Pikes, and let the Lord Judge who hath obſerved the Ends of the <hi>Covenant</hi> beſt, you or we; Yet we do acknowledge, We have not been the exact Performers, though not the wilful Breakers thereof: Our conſciences alſo bear us record, We do above any thing in the world, deſire the Union of the two Nations; and it is our prayer daily, That thoſe that fear the Lord in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> may become one in the hand of the Lord, and joyn together in the advancement of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and throwing down, and trampling upon the Seat of the Beaſt. Why ſhould not <hi>Scotland,</hi> as well as <hi>England,</hi> rejoyce to ſee the Horns of the Beaſt cut off, that we may joyn together, to hate the Whore, and <hi>to burn her fleſh with ſire?</hi> The Lord is our witneſs (whom we fear) we come not to oppreſs you, or ſhed your blood; we have cryed to the Lord again and again to prevent it; we have ſent our Declarations of love to the People of God in <hi>Scotland</hi> which ſome amongſt you, though they pretend to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, yet do moſt injuriouſly and unchriſtianly keep from their ſight, nay moſt falſly miſrepreſenting us as a people come with intentions to deſtroy the poor Inhabitants, and that we are left of our God to be deſtroyed: but we have made our prayer to the Lord, and made known before him their ſayings, who hath told the people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> That God hath forſaken us; and therefore bid them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute and take us, for now the Sectaries day is come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Lord is ſtill with us, he is our Refuge, and a preſent help in trouble, ready to be found: we do believe, the cry of the oppreſſed in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will be heard, and wo be to thoſe that are the cauſe thereof. Our Quarrel is ſtill againſt Malignants, the Root whereof is now, through the evil policy of ſome Stateſmen, become the Head of <hi>Scotland.</hi> We dare not quarrel with thoſe whoſe hearts are upright with Jeſus Chriſt, and faithful and loving to <hi>England,</hi> but with thoſe who are moſt treacherous and falſe to both; and therefore we dare not any of us, though tempted thereto by your Papers, be ſo carnally wiſe, as to deſert the Cauſe and Work of Jeſus Chriſt, in which we have hitherto been ſo long and ſo miraculouſly carried on. Do you think we are men ſo weakly principled, as to be perſwaded without the leaſt ſtrength of Argument, to deſert the Intereſt of our own Nation, and expoſe thouſands of the precious Saints of Jeſus Chriſt, to be trampled upon as the dirt in the ſtreets, when the Lord is about
<pb facs="tcp:117409:9"/>to put on their beautiful garments, and to make them a praiſe in the earth? Or can we (think you) betray our ſuperior Officers, in whom we ſee ſo much of the ſweet Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt, into your hands, whoſe mouthes are opened wide to devour them: we pray you not to wait for ſuch a thing. The Lord hath brought us hither by his Providence, and upon him we ſhall with confidence depend, till we ſee a glorious iſſue, which we humbly and heartily deſire may be without the effuſion of any more blood; and (if it be the will of God) both ſpeedy and comfortable to you and us, that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn with joy into <hi>England,</hi> and leave <hi>Scotland</hi> rejoycing, that an Engliſh Army hath been amongſt them, which poſſibly may be the ſooner effected, were you and we ſuffered to confer and open our hearts one to another: we do believe much of the bitterneſs of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit would be allayed in our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> did they know how exceedingly we are ſlandred by the pens and tongues of many of your Kirkmen, concerning our Religion and Faith towards God, which though we may not vainly boaſt of, yet according to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles direction, we are ready to give an anſwer to the meaneſt Chriſtian in <hi>Scotland, that ſhall ask a reaſon of the faith and hope that is in us with meekneſs and fear.</hi> And indeed we account our beſt way of contending with thoſe Slanderers, is to pray the Lord to make our hearts ſound in his Statutes, that we be not aſhamed, that ſo we <hi>ſanctifying the Lord God in our hearts, and having a good conſcience, they that speak evil of us as of evil doers, may be aſhamed whileſt they falſly our good converſation in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we have in the naked plainneſs of our ſouls opened our hearts unto you our dear Brethren that fear the Lord in <hi>Scotland,</hi> where-ever you be found, whether in the higheſt Councels or the pooreſt Cottages, who though you now lie ſcattered, the Lord will in his due time bring you together, and binde you up as his Jewels, and make you one with thoſe that fear the Lord amongſt us, which the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and in him our God and our Father alſo, bring to paſs in his due time; and in the mean time make both you and us wiſe to underſtand the things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the exalting of Chriſts Kingdom: That in all our undertakings we may be ſubſervient to the affairs of Jeſus Chriſt, and above all things take heed how we ſtir up any of the powers or ſtrength of this world, to deſtroy one another. <hi>The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Prince of Peace, be with you.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From the Leaguer at Muſcleborough, <date>Auguſt 1.1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
